Dario Amodei is the CEO of Anthropic. He's
다리오 아모데이는 앤스로픽의 CEO입니다. 그는
also, I think, one of the most vocal
또한 제 생각에는 가장 목소리를 크게 내는
truth-tellers about the good, the bad, and
AI의 좋은 점과 나쁜 점, 그리고
the potential ugly and destruction from AI.
AI가 가져올 수 있는 추악한 면과 파괴에 대해 진실을 말하는 사람 중 한 명입니다.
We had a spur-of-the-moment chance
우리는 즉흥적으로 기회를 얻어
to talk to Dario. His memo was out.
다리오와 이야기할 수 있었습니다. 그의 메모가 공개돼 있었습니다.
We said we wanted to go a little
우리는 조금 더
deeper with him. The way that Dario says,
깊이 이야기해 보고 싶다고 말했습니다. 다리오가 말하는 방식은,
if five words, humanity needs to wake up.
다섯 단어로 말하면 인류는 깨어나야 합니다.
Last year, when he made that warning that
작년에 그가 그런 경고를 했을 때,
50% of white-collar jobs could be
화이트칼라 일자리의 50%가
obsolete within a couple years because of AI,
AI 때문에 몇 년 안에 쓸모없어질 수 있다고 말했을 때,
he ignited a national conversation. With this memo,
그는 전국적인 대화를 촉발했습니다. 이번 메모에서,
he's taking a different track. He's trying to
그는 다른 경로를 택하고 있습니다. 그는
say it's not just jobs. It could be
말하려고 합니다. 이것은 일자리만의 문제가 아니라고요. 이것은
your national security. It could be your way
국가 안보일 수도 있습니다. 이것은 여러분의
of life. And it was written to be
삶의 방식일 수도 있습니다. 그리고 그것은
provocative. It is provocative.
도발적으로 쓰이도록 작성됐습니다. 그것은 도발적입니다.
One of his biggest warnings, along with authoritarian
권위주의 정부들과 함께 그가 가장 크게 경고한 것 중 하나는
governments, was AI companies. He said, it's awkward
AI 기업들이었습니다. 그는 AI 기업의 수장으로서 이런 말을 하기가 어색하다고 했습니다.
for me to say this as the head
그가 말했습니다. 저는 이런 말을 하는 것이
of an AI company, but look at all
AI 기업의 대표로서 어색하지만, 모든
of the users that they have. Look at
사용자 수를 보십시오. 그리고
all the data centers they have. Look at
그들이 가진 모든 데이터센터를 보십시오. 그리고
all the power they have. And what if
그들이 가진 모든 권력을 보십시오. 그리고 만약
they were to brainwash this massive consumer use
그들이 이 거대한 소비자 사용자 기반을 세뇌한다면
base? That was new to me, Jim.
어떻게 되겠습니까? 그것은 제게 새로웠습니다, 짐.
It's a wake-up call that people need
사람들이 응답해야 할 경종입니다.
to answer. They need to listen. You might
사람들은 답해야 합니다. 사람들은 들어야 합니다. 여러분은
be skeptical. You might be scared. You might
회의적일 수도 있습니다. 두려울 수도 있습니다. 여러분은
be enthusiastic. What Dario has to say is
열광적일 수도 있습니다. 다리오가 말하는 것은
important. And by the way, it synthesizes provocatively,
중요합니다. 그리고 덧붙이자면, 그것은 도발적으로 종합하지만,
but I think accurately, what we hear in
제 생각에는 정확하게도, 우리가
conversation after conversation with other people. It's not
다른 사람들과의 대화 또 대화에서 듣는 것을 종합합니다. 이것은
him just being hysterical. I don't think it's
그가 그저 히스테릭해하는 것이 아닙니다. 저는 이것이
him just hyping the technology. I think it
그가 그저 기술을 과장하는 것만은 아니라고 생각합니다. 제가 보기에는
is he reflects a concern we hear time
그것은 그가 우리가 거듭해서 듣는 우려를 반영하기 때문입니다.
and time again, at least in off-the
적어도 비공개
-record conversations,
대화에서,
with the people that are building these technologies
이 기술들을 만들고 있는 사람들과
and using them. And we wanted to go
이를 사용하는 사람들로부터요. 그리고 우리는
beyond the memo. We wanted to talk specifically
메모를 넘어가고 싶었습니다. 우리는 특히
about what message, if it was delivered in
만약 가장 직설적인 형태로 전달된다면 어떤 메시지를
its bluntest form, would Dario want to deliver
다리오가 전달하고 싶어 하는지에 대해 이야기하고 싶었습니다.
to members of Congress and members of the
의회 의원들과
federal government?
연방 정부 구성원들에게요?
What are the three things that you wish
지금 의회가 했으면 하는 세 가지는 무엇입니까?
Congress would do now? And then also, what
그리고 또, 정말로 무엇이 벌어지고 있는지에 능통하고
do you wish they would tell their constituents
완전히 솔직하게 말한다면, 그들이 유권자들에게
if they were really fluent on what's going
무엇을 말하길 바라십니까?
on and they were completely leveling with them?
상황을 정확히 이해한 채로 말입니다.
Yeah. So I think three things to do
네. 그러면 지금 해야 할 일 세 가지를 말씀드리겠습니다.
now. One would be like transparency legislation as
첫째는 가능한 한 강력한 투명성 관련 입법입니다.
robust as possible. What tests did you run?
어떤 테스트를 했습니까?
What are you seeing with respect to your
당신들의 모델과 관련해서는 무엇을 보고 있습니까?
model? Companies have the capability to study these
기업들은 이런 것들을 연구할 역량이
things and they often do. And so kind
있고, 실제로 자주 합니다. 그래서
of requiring that they not only study these
그들이 이런 위험을 연구하도록 요구할 뿐 아니라
risks, but show those risks to the public,
그 위험을 대중에게 보여주도록 요구하는 것입니다.
put a label on the product.
제품에 라벨을 붙이도록 하는 것입니다.
I think that's really helpful to the consumer.
그것은 소비자에게 정말로 도움이 된다고 생각합니다.
And it's also helpful in that it allows
또한 이는 기업들이 서로에게서 배우게 해 준다는 점에서도 도움이 됩니다.
companies to learn from each other. If each
각 기업이
company is studying these things on its own
각자 이런 것들을 연구하고
and is afraid to show what it's finding
경쟁 때문에 자신들이 발견한 것을
to others because of competition, we can't learn
다른 이들에게 보여주길 두려워한다면,
about these things as a scientific community.
우리는 과학 공동체로서
I think the second thing, and I've said
이런 것들을 배울 수 없습니다.
it many times, but it's hard enough between
둘째는, 제가 여러 번 말해 왔지만,
the companies in the U.S. to handle
미국 내 기업들 사이에서도
this crazy commercial race. But in theory, we
이 미친 상업적 경쟁을 다루는 것만으로도 충분히 어렵습니다. 하지만 이론적으로는
could pass laws like I just described that
방금 제가 설명한 것 같은 법을 통과시켜
help to rein the companies in.
기업들을 견제하는 데 도움이 되게 할 수 있습니다.
But it's almost impossible to do that if
하지만 권위주의적 적대국이 밖에서
we have an authoritarian adversary who's out there
우리만큼이나 빠르게
building the technology almost as fast as we
기술을 만들고 있다면, 그런 일은 거의 불가능합니다.
are, right? It creates a terrible dilemma. And
그렇지 않습니까? 이것은 끔찍한 딜레마를 만듭니다. 그리고
I think we need to cut off the
저는 우리가 공급망을
supply chain. We're years ahead of them in
차단해야 한다고 생각합니다. 우리는 칩에서 그들보다 수년 앞서 있습니다.
chips. We really can. We really can cut
우리는 정말로 할 수 있습니다. 우리는 정말로 공급망을
off the supply chain.
차단할 수 있습니다.
And that gives us the time and the
그리고 그것은 우리에게 시간과
buffer to deal with these dangers properly. And
완충을 제공해 이런 위험들을 제대로 다룰 수 있게 해 줍니다. 그리고
then third, I think we need to think
셋째로, 저는 우리가 이 기술의 혜택
about the distribution of benefits of this technology.
분배에 대해 생각해야 한다고 봅니다.
I see AI creating a world where there's
저는 AI가 엄청난 경제 성장을 만들어내는 세상을 만들 것이라고 봅니다.
enormous economic growth, right? We can cure cancer.
암을 치료할 수 있습니다.
We can, you know, develop energy for cheaper.
더 저렴한 에너지를 개발할 수 있습니다.
We can develop enormous new materials. And those
엄청나게 새로운 재료를 개발할 수도 있습니다. 그리고 그런 것들이
things will grow the economy enormously. But precisely
경제를 엄청나게 성장시킬 것입니다. 하지만 바로
because AI does the jobs that, you know,
AI가, 그러니까,
many current white collar workers do, you know,
현재 많은 화이트칼라 근로자들이 하는 일들을 수행하기 때문에,
that there's going to be some concentration of
노동에서 자본으로 부가 이전되면서
this wealth from labor to capital.
이 부가 어느 정도 집중될 것입니다.
And so we're going to have this weird
그래서 우리는 이전에는 본 적이 거의 없는
world that we've really never seen before where,
이상한 세상을 맞게 될 것입니다. 즉,
you know, we have enormous wealth, but distribution
엄청난 부가 있지만, 분배가
is a problem. That's a different world. I
문제인 세상입니다. 그것은 다른 세상입니다. 저는
don't think it's an ideological thing, but I
그것이 이념적인 문제라고 생각하지 않지만,
think we just need to adjust to that
우리는 그 세상에 적응해야
world.
한다고 생각합니다.
How do you adjust to that now? Like,
지금 그것에 어떻게 적응하시겠습니까?
obviously, we don't have that. That's not the
분명히 우리에게는 그런 현실이 없습니다. 그것은
reality today. So, like, how would Congress prepare
오늘날의 현실이 아닙니다. 그래서, 의회는 어떻게
the country to do that so we're not
국가가 그에 대비하도록 해서 우리가
caught napping and having to do it retroactively?
잠자다가 소급적으로 대응하지 않도록 하겠습니까?
Maybe the most obvious one is, you know,
아마도 가장 명백한 것은,
we kind of need to think about more
더 강력한 조세 정책에 대해
robust tax policies, you know, and, you know,
생각해야 한다는 것입니다. 그리고,
I don't think this is the tax policies
저는 이것이 과거의
of old. This is for a world where
조세 정책이라고 생각하지 않습니다. 이것은
people are trillionaires. We're almost there already with
조만장자가 있는 세상을 위한 것입니다. 일론 머스크로
Elon Musk.
거의 그 수준에 와 있습니다.
And I think the effect of AI and
그리고 저는 AI의 효과와
the effect of the AI companies is going
AI 기업들의 효과가
to make that more extreme. And, you know,
그것을 더 극단적으로 만들 것이라고 생각합니다. 그리고,
I say that as, you know, one of
저는 그것의 혜택을 받는
the people who's benefiting from it, right?
사람 중 한 명으로서 말하는 것입니다, 그렇지요?
If we don't find a well-designed answer
이 문제에 대해 잘 설계된 답을 찾지 못하면
to this problem, we may get poorly designed
잘못 설계된 답을 얻게 될 수도
answers, right? We may get, you know, kind
있습니다. 그렇지요? 우리는
of very aggressive, poorly designed answers.
매우 공격적이고 잘못 설계된 답을 얻게 될 수도 있습니다.
And so I guess my ask would be,
그래서 제 부탁은 이렇습니다.
look, there's going to be this skew in
부의 분배에 편향이 생길 것입니다.
distribution of wealth. What are ways of handling
경제적으로 문해력 있고
it that are economically literate and economically sensible
경제적으로 합리적인 방식으로 이를 다루는 방법은 무엇입니까?
so that we don't get this crazy knee
그래서 우리가 이런 미친
-jerk stuff?
즉흥적 반응을 피할 수 있도록요?
Dario, these are heavy, heavy lifts. Members of
다리오, 이것들은 매우 무거운 과제입니다. 제가
Congress I talk to are afraid to even
대화하는 의회 의원들은 이 문제에 대해
talk about this issue, like their constituents either
얘기하는 것조차 두려워합니다. 그들의 유권자들은
are worried about their jobs or pissed about
일자리를 걱정하거나 전기요금에 화가 나 있거나
their power bills or they think it's icky
불쾌하다고 생각하거나
or they're queasy.
불안해합니다.
How do you convince policy lawmakers, both ends
펜실베이니아 애비뉴 양끝의 정책 결정자들에게
of Pennsylvania Avenue, that they can, must talk
이 문제들에 대해 이야기할 수 있고 반드시 이야기해야 한다고
about these issues, dig in?
파고들어야 한다고 어떻게 설득하시겠습니까?
So it's not going to happen in a
하루아침에 되지는 않을 것입니다.
day. But what I will say is as
하지만 제가 말씀드리고 싶은 것은
we see the effects of AI, you know,
AI의 효과를 보면서,
I expect the public to understand that AI
대중이 AI가 이 모든 놀라운 것들을,
is bringing us all these wonders, all these
이 모든 의료의 경이를,
medical wonders, all this, you know, abundance.
이 모든 풍요를 가져다준다는 것을 이해할 것으로 기대합니다.
Eventually we'll get cheap robots that will, you
결국에는 모든 것을 할
know, will do everything. But these problems will
저렴한 로봇을 갖게 될 것입니다. 하지만 이런 문제들이
emerge. People will say, where are my jobs?
등장할 것입니다. 사람들은 '내 일자리는 어디에 있나요?'라고 물을 것입니다.
People will say, why is that person a
사람들은 '왜 저 사람은
trillionaire and my wage has gone down because
조만장자이고 제 임금은 내려갔나요?
I've been de-skilled, right? People ask these
제 기술이 쓸모없어졌기 때문입니다'라고 물을 것입니다. 사람들은 이런
questions. And I think it's better if you
질문을 합니다. 그리고 저는 미리 앞서 나가서
get ahead of it and you start to
지금부터 생각하기 시작하는 것이
think about it now.
더 낫다고 생각합니다.
And by the way, I don't think it'll
그리고 덧붙이자면, 이것이 당파적
be a partisan thing. It's not even a
문제가 될 것이라고 생각하지 않습니다. 지금도 당파적이지
partisan thing now. Even people on the two
않습니다. 제가 대화한
extremes of the political spectrum I've talked to,
정치적 스펙트럼의 양 극단에 있는 사람들도,
and it's remarkable how similar the things they
그들이 하는 말이 얼마나 비슷한지
say are.
놀랍습니다.
Do you think that any of your fellow
동료 미래 조만장자들 중
future trillionaires will be for this, will discuss
이것을 지지하고, 논의하거나,
it, or will they fight it?
아니면 그들이 싸울 것이라고 생각하십니까?
You know, I can't say what anyone else
다른 사람이 무엇을 할지는
is going to do, right? Like, you know,
말할 수 없습니다. 그렇지요?
I don't...
저는...
But you know these...
하지만 당신은 그들을 아시잖아요...
You know the future fellow trillionaires. What can
미래의 동료 조만장자들을 아시잖아요. 당신의
you do to bring them along with how
생각에 그들을 동참시키려면 무엇을
you're thinking? As I can tell you, a
하실 수 있습니까? 말씀드리자면,
lot of them aren't there now.
그들 중 많은 수가 지금은 거기에 있지 않습니다.
Yeah, yeah. I agree many are not there
네, 네. 많은 분들이 지금은 거기에
now. I mean, there's, you know, there's a
있지 않다는 데 동의합니다. 제 말은,
wide range of views. And again, I can't
다양한 견해가 있습니다. 그리고 다시 말하지만, 저는
speak for anyone else. But I would just
다른 누구도 대변할 수 없습니다. 하지만 저는
say the thing I said before.
전에 말한 것을 다시 말씀드리겠습니다.
You can't just go around saying like, okay,
그냥 돌아다니면서 '좋아요,
you know, we're going to create all this
우리가 이 모든 풍요를
abundance. A lot of it is going to
창출할 거예요. 그 많은 부분이
go to us. And, you know, we're going
우리에게 갈 거예요. 그리고
to be trillionaires. And, you know, no one's
우리가 조만장자가 될 거예요. 그리고 아무도
going to complain about that.
그것에 대해 불평하지 않을 거예요'라고 말할 수는 없습니다.
No one's going to try and do anything,
아무도 어떤 시도도 하지 않을 것이다,
right? You know, if your answer is just
그렇지요? 만약 당신의 답이 그냥
screw you, there's nothing we can or should
'알 바 아니고, 우리가 할 수 있거나 해야 할
do about this, then, you know, that's going
일은 없다'라면, 그것은
to create a lot of discontent.
많은 불만을 만들 것입니다.
It already has. We're already starting to see
이미 그렇습니다. 우리는 이미 그
the beginnings of it. And it's just going
시작을 보고 있습니다. 그리고 그것은 더 나빠질
to get worse. And so my view is
것입니다. 그래서 제 견해는 이것이 옳은 일이기 때문에
we should do this because it's the right
해야 한다는 것입니다.
thing to do.
옳은 일이니까요.
But if I were to talk to others,
하지만 다른 사람들과 이야기한다면,
if that isn't compelling to them, and I
그것이 그들에게 설득력이 없다면, 그리고 저는
hope it is, but if that isn't compelling
설득력이 있기를 바라지만, 그것이 그들에게 설득력이
to them, then I would say, look, you're
없다면, 저는 '보세요,
going to get a mob coming for you
이것을 올바른 방식으로 하지 않으면
if you don't do this in the right
폭도들이 당신에게
way.
몰려올 것입니다'라고 말할 것입니다.
If you don't do this in the wrong
잘못된 방식으로 하지 않고 올바른 방식으로 하지 않으면,
way, in the right way, it's going to
매우 잘못된 방식으로
happen in a very wrong way.
일어나게 될 것입니다.
What should members of Congress be telling their
의회 의원들은 AI의 상태와 향후 1년간
constituents about the state of AI and where
우리가 어디로 향하고 있는지에 대해
we're headed over the next year?
유권자들에게 무엇을 말해야 합니까?
We have an interesting situation in AI in
AI에서 흥미로운 상황이 있습니다.
that, you know, people are concerned about it.
사람들이 그것에 대해 걱정하고 있습니다.
Broadly, that concern is, you know, is well
대체로 그 우려는
justified. But I don't know that it's all
정당합니다. 하지만 그것이 모두
that well targeted.
정확히 겨냥되어 있는지는 모르겠습니다.
You know, there are risks like, say, you
예를 들어 AI의 물 사용량 같은
know, the water use of AI that, you
위험이 있는데,
know, if you look into it, AI actually
살펴보면 AI는 실제로
doesn't use that much water.
그렇게 많은 물을 사용하지 않습니다.
There are many problems with AI, but that's
AI에는 많은 문제가 있지만 그것은
not one of them. And then, of course,
그중 하나가 아닙니다. 그리고 물론,
people are worried about their power bills, which
사람들은 전기요금을 걱정하는데, 저는 그것이
I think is understandable and kind of well
이해할 만하고 어느 정도는 꽤
targeted.
핵심을 잘 찌른다고 생각합니다.
But, you know, I think in the long
하지만, 아시다시피 장기적으로 보면 저는
run, it's not about power bills. It's about
전기요금 문제가 아닙니다. 핵심은
enormous abundance and whether they get their piece
막대한 풍요로움과 사람들이 그
of the abundance.
풍요로움에서 자신의 몫을 가져가느냐입니다.
Maybe power bills is like a little tiny
전기요금은 어쩌면 아주 작은
piece of that. So, you know, I would
부분에 불과합니다. 그래서 저는
say constituents are concerned, but, you know, helping
유권자들이 걱정하긴 하지만, 그들에게
to educate them about where things are going,
상황이 어디로 가고 있는지 교육하고,
helping to bring them along.
함께 따라오도록 돕는 것이 도움이 된다고 말씀드리겠습니다.
Because, again, I'd say the same thing. Like,
왜냐하면, 다시 말씀드리지만 저는 늘 같은 말을 합니다.
if you don't lead, if you don't say
리더십을 발휘하지 않고, '이것이
this is where things are going and we're,
앞으로의 방향입니다'라고 말하지 않으면, 우리는
you know, we're looking hard for solutions, you
해결책을 열심히 찾고 있습니다,
know, even if we don't have all the
비록 아직 모든
answers yet, like we've got your back, we're
답을 갖고 있지는 않더라도, '우리가 여러분을 지켜드리겠습니다,
trying to find the solutions here.
해결책을 찾으려고 노력하고 있습니다'라고 말해야 합니다.
I think that will end much better than
그렇게 하는 편이
saying there's nothing to worry about here or
'걱정할 게 없습니다'라고 말하거나
only, you know, we're only looking at these
그저 '우리는 이런
very, these kind of very limited problems.
아주 제한적인 문제들만 보고 있다'고 하는 것보다 훨씬 나을 것입니다.
And the assumption in Washington is because President
그리고 워싱턴에서는 트럼프 대통령과
Trump, David Sachs and others want to be
데이비드 색스 등 여러 사람들이
hands off on AI and have the U
AI에 대해 간섭하지 않으려 하고 미국이
.S. win the race against China.
중국과의 경쟁에서 이기길 원하기 때문에 그렇다는 전제가 있습니다.
Congress seems to have no appetite to intervene.
의회는 개입할 의지가 없어 보입니다.
What outlined the risks of waiting three years
3년을 기다리며 아무것도 하지 않을 때의 위험을
to do anything, which seems like the most
설명해 주시겠습니까? 솔직히 말해
likely scenario right now, if we're being honest.
지금으로서는 그것이 가장 가능성 높은 시나리오처럼 보입니다.
Yeah. So, you know, you know, I think,
네. 그러니까, 제 생각에는,
I think, I think if we wait three
만약 우리가 3년을
years, like this technology is progressing exponentially, right?
기다리면, 이 기술은 기하급수적으로 발전하고 있지 않습니까?
Three years ago in 2023, the models were
3년 전인 2023년에는 모델이
maybe as smart as like a smart high
아마도 똑똑한 고등
school student.
학교 학생 정도의 수준이었습니다.
Now we have engineers at Anthropic where the
지금은 앤트로픽에서 모델이
model writes all the code for them, you
엔지니어를 위해 모든 코드를 작성하고,
know, and the engineer maybe edits it.
엔지니어는 그것을 조금 편집하는 정도인 경우도 있습니다.
But we're very close to, you know, mid
하지만 우리는 이제 중간
to high professional level. Right.
에서 고급 전문 수준에 아주 가까워졌습니다. 그렇지요.
And so that was just in three years.
그런 변화가 고작 3년 만에 일어났습니다.
If we wait another year, three years, I
앞으로 1년, 3년을 더 기다리면 저는
think we'll get what I call in the
제가 에세이에서
essay, our country of geniuses in the data
'데이터센터 속의 천재들로 이루어진 우리나라'라고 부르는 것을
center, maybe less than three years.
아마 3년도 안 되어 보게 될 것이라고 생각합니다.
And so, you know, three years is an
그러니, 3년은 이
eternity in this field.
분야에서는 영원에 가깝습니다.
And so I think we absolutely need to
그래서 우리는 반드시
act before then.
그 전에 행동해야 한다고 생각합니다.
One place where I really have hope is
제가 정말 희망을 갖는 지점 하나는
I think as these problems start to manifest,
이런 문제들이 나타나기 시작하면
again, they're not going to be partisan, right?
다시 말해, 그것이 당파적 이슈가 되지는 않을 것이라는 점입니다. 그렇지요?
Like, you know, it may start with, you
예컨대 처음에는, 어떤
know, one party or one side having an
정당이나 한쪽 진영이
anti-regulatory ideology.
반규제 이념을 갖는 데서 출발할 수도 있습니다.
But I think as these problems become real,
하지만 이런 문제들이 현실이 되면,
there's going to be a demand among everyone.
모두에게서 대응을 요구하는 목소리가 나오게 될 것입니다.
And in the note, you outline the different
그리고 메모에서 여러
risks, whether it's bioterror or whether it's authoritarian
위험을 정리하셨지요. 생물테러이든, 권위주의
regimes with too many tools to do subversive
정권이 전복적
behavior.
행동을 할 수 있는 도구를 너무 많이 갖게 되는 것이든요.
Like what?
예를 들면 어떤 것들입니까?
Like how worried are you?
그리고 얼마나 걱정하고 계신가요?
I mean, you're obviously worried enough to state
말씀하실 정도면 분명
it and you're worried enough to raise it.
걱정이 크셔서 문제를 제기하시는 것인데,
But like in your mind, how likely is
하지만 대표님께서는
that outcome, particularly if we don't do anything
그런 결과가, 특히 우리가 아무것도 하지 않으면
for the next three years?
향후 3년 동안 얼마나 일어날 가능성이 있다고 보십니까?
Is it like a 1% or like,
1% 정도입니까, 아니면
no, no, if you don't do anything for
아니요, 아니요, 3년 동안
three years, like we could be screwed.
아무것도 하지 않으면 정말 큰일 날 수 있다는 수준입니까?
Yeah, it's always hard to tell.
네, 그것은 언제나 판단하기 어렵습니다.
One of the things I say in the
제가 에세이에서 말한 것 중 하나는
essay is, you know, we just don't know,
우리는 정말로 모른다는 점입니다.
right?
그렇지요?
We could look back and we could say,
나중에 돌아보며 이렇게 말할 수도 있습니다.
ha-ha, AI-driven bioterror.
'하하, AI 주도 생물테러라니.'
You know, that was, you know, that sounded
그때는, 그러니까,
like it could happen at the time.
그럴듯하게 들리긴 했지만,
But like, you know, it just didn't happen
결국 실제로는 전혀
at all.
일어나지 않았다고요.
And it's very unpredictable.
그리고 그것은 매우 예측 불가능합니다.
You know, the way I would say it
제 표현으로 말하면,
is we're taking a paranoid stance with respect
우리는 운영 방식에서
to our operational behavior, with respect to them.
그런 위험들에 대해 편집증적일 정도로 경계하는 자세를 취하고 있습니다.
We always assume that everything that can go
우리는 잘못될 수 있는
wrong does go wrong.
모든 일은 실제로 잘못된다고 항상 가정합니다.
That's how you build things that are reliable,
그래야 신뢰할 수 있는 것을 만들 수 있습니다.
right?
그렇지요?
If you're building a rocket, you're not like,
로켓을 만든다고 해서,
oh, yeah, I'm sure this part will work
'아, 이 부품은 분명 잘 작동하겠지'라고
out.
생각하지는 않습니다.
I'm sure this thing will survive the tensile
'이것이 인장
forces.
하중을 견디겠지'라고도요.
You're like, no, I'm going to do a
대신 '아니, 나는
scenario analysis of this and that and that
이것과 저것과 또 다른 것들에 대해
and the other thing.
시나리오 분석을 하겠다'고 합니다.
You know, I'm not going to take anything
그러니까, 저는 어떤 것도
for granted.
당연하게 여기지 않겠습니다.
And, yeah, you know, if government steps in
그리고, 만약 정부가 나서서
and takes the appropriate actions, then I think
적절한 조치를 취한다면 저는
our chances of success go up a lot.
성공 가능성이 크게 올라간다고 생각합니다.
We'll do the best we can, even if
그렇지 않더라도 우리는 가능한
that doesn't happen.
최선을 다하겠습니다.
But, you know, I think a lot of
하지만 정책결정자들이
things get easier if our policymakers are not
운전대를 놓고
asleep at the wheel.
잠들어 있지 않다면 많은 일이 더 쉬워질 것입니다.
I think we're getting the hook, Daria.
이제 마무리해야 할 것 같습니다, 다리오님.
We appreciate you taking time to do this.
시간 내주셔서 감사합니다.
Memo is fascinating.
메모가 정말 흥미롭습니다.
The manifesto is great.
선언문도 훌륭합니다.
So we appreciate it.
정말 감사드립니다.
Thank you for the conversation.
대화해 주셔서 감사합니다.
How long did you work on the memo?
메모는 얼마나 오래 작업하셨나요?
So I wrote it.
제가 직접 썼습니다.
I wrote the first draft in 72 hours
첫 초안을 72시간 만에 썼습니다.
over winter break.
겨울 휴가 동안입니다.
You know, honestly, my winter break is like
솔직히 제 겨울 휴가는
I spend a week just zoning out and
일주일은 그냥 멍하니
playing video games.
비디오게임을 하며 보내고,
And then, like, in the last three days
그리고 휴가 마지막 3일에는
of winter break, I was like, oh, man,
속으로 '아, 이제는' 하고
I should I should, like, try and get
뭔가 제대로
something right.
해봐야겠다고 생각했습니다.
And so and so I wrote for, like,
그래서, 그러니까,
72 hours, almost almost without almost without sleeping.
거의 잠도 자지 않고 72시간 동안 썼습니다.
How much of it was Claude?
그중 얼마나 많은 부분을 클로드가 했나요?
Claude did not write any of it.
클로드는 그 어떤 부분도 쓰지 않았습니다.
Claude helped me, though, to do a fair
다만 클로드가 제가
amount of fair amount of research.
상당한 조사를 하는 데 도움이 되었고,
And Claude gave feedback.
클로드가 피드백도 주었습니다.
I would I would say I was the
저는 제가 작가였고
writer and Claude was kind of my editor
클로드는 제 편집자이자
and my research assistant.
리서치 어시스턴트였다고 말씀드리겠습니다.
Drop the mic.
마이크를 내려놓겠습니다.
Thanks for the time.
시간 내주셔서 감사합니다.